Guide to the Ruth Asawa Papers M1585
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 25. Audiovisual Media and Photographs
  - 25.1 interviews, news profiles, etc.
    - Ruth Asawa on Internment, 1990; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Side A: Addie Lanier interviews her mother Ruth Asawa for Noe Valley Voice "Voices of Noe Valley" article; [15:45] Addie Lanier telephone conversations re: other NVV articles, personal/family. Side B: more interview, mostly re: internment.
    - CAC [California Arts Council], 1990-11; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 45, Folder 12)
      "State of the Arts" program with host Bob Reid. interview with Asawa. Sacramento public television? Partially funded by CAC.
    - Ruth Asawa, Channel 4 News With Belva Davis [KRON], 1991-07-04; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Brief KRON profile.
    - CBS Sunday Morning Ruth Asawa "Changed By Art." FP-94-7952, 1994-07-31; 2 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 44, Folder 1)
      CBS Sunday Morning profile by Jerry Bowen. Ruth at Santa Anita race track, sketching (see original in Internment files), San Jose Internment Memorial opening, Alvarado. Asawa segment begins 28:41 in full episode.
    - Internment Interview by Joanne Iritani for the Florin JACL, 2000-04-07; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Iritani interviews Asawa about her life and art. "She got a civil liberties grant to interview camp/Japanese American experience. Interview done Spring/Summer 2000." See transcript in Writing and Transcripts series.
    - Excerpts From a Research Interview of Ruth Asawa by Karin Higa and Sally Stein. Japanese American National Museum, 2001-09-07; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 44, Folder 3)
      Produced program with interviews of Asawa in her house.
    - Ruth Asawa and Albert Lanier Re: Valerie Harper [TK Zung interviews], 2002; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 43, Folder 2)
      Video made for Valerie Harper by TK Zung. 1. Ruth Asawa 2. Ruth Asawa and Albert Lanier 3. Ring Designed by Bucky Fuller for Ruth. Zung interviews Asawa and Lanier, 2002. Met actress Harper through Blanche Pastorino, involved with Hunger Project along with John Denver, Buckminster Fuller. She invited them to her play when it was in SF. see other Zung interviews, some same content.
    - Ruth Asawa Retrospective Broadcast [KNBR], 2002-05-25; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 41, Folder 11)
      radio interview with Gimmy Park Li, host of untitled public affairs program on KNBR.
    - Ruth Asawa Preview Video. Bridge Media, Inc., 2002-06-02; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 44, Folder 4)
      Asawa profile, opens with new de Young, closes with San Jose Internment Memorial. Made before SFSU Garden video, also by Bridge Media.
    - Ruth Asawa KGO-TV Profiles in Excellence, 2003-08-05; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Profiles in Excellence series, hosted by Thuy Vu. Asian Art Museum, community leaders profiled. 6:54-11:57 Asawa segment
    - Oakland Museum of California Interview With Ruth Asawa by Suzanne Baizerman. San Francisco. [Tape 1 of 2 only], 2003-09-18; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Unedited interview by Baizerman in Ruth's home.
    - D. Cornell Interview on Pacific Currents, KQED Radio [about Asawa], 2006-12; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 41, Folder 12)
      Side B: Pacific Time, host Patricia Flynn. Radio interview with Daniell Cornell, de Young exhibit curator, author of Asawa book; [19:29] fishing program cont.
    - Asawa Symposium at de Young. D. Cornell, M. Johnson, V. Matsumoto, Lenore Chin, 2007-01-06; 2 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 44, Folder 7)
      de Young Museum Symposium on Ruth Asawa. Harry Parker (introduced by John Buchanan) [25:29]; short talks and panel discussion by Daniell Cornell, Valerie Matsumoto, Mark Johnson, and Lenore Chinn. Questions and remarks from audience not audible.
  - 25.2 de Young book interviews by Aiko Cuneo and Addie Lanier, 2003-2004
    - BMC & Ruth (after BMC State College) #13. 4; Ruth BMC ends with #31. 3, 2003; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 79, Folder 1)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa about art and class notes at Black Mountain College. Side A: #12B cont-17, 2003-12-10. Side B: #18-31. Albers, studio, San Francisco State, etc.
    - BMC work found later. Starts 1a; BMC cont. #47, 2003; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 79, Folder 2)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa about art and class notes at Black Mountain College.
    - BMC Transcribed 12/26/03, 2003; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - BMC - Ruth 12/5/03 Starts With #1. 1; BMC Ruth 12/5/03 Ends With #4, Starts With #5 & On. 2, 2003-12; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 79, Folder 4)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa about art and class notes at Black Mountain College. Side A: #1-4. Side B: #4 cont, #5-12b.
    - Ruth BMC starts with #31, Ends With #41. 5; Ruth BMC/SF Starts With #42 Ends With #49 & On. 6. #37 Between 30 & 50 [note], 2003; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 79, Folder 5)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa. Side A: #31 cont.-41, 2003-12-10. Side B: no numbers
    - Aiko Cuneo interviews Ruth Asawa for de Young book (Transcribed). Early Inspirations - Woven Wire - Tied Wire - Electroplating - Cast Pieces, 2003; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 42, Folder 2)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa about her art. 1. 2003-09-24 tied wire; 2/3. 2003-10-20 woven wire; 4. 2003-09-24 electroplated wire.
    - Addie Lanier interviews Ruth Asawa and Albert Lanier in prep for De Young Book. Fact-checking, 2004-07-20; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Ruth Early Childhood/Art; Early Childhood, Camp, College. Both Sides Transcribed, 2003-12-09; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 54, Folder 13)
      Aiko Cuneo interviews her mother Ruth Asawa about her childhood, upbringing, education, and early artistic tendencies.
    - Albert's Stories 9/18/03 & 12/26/03; 11-24-03 Ruth- BMC, Bucky Ring, Coming to CA. Transcribed, 2003; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 54, Folder 14)
      Side A: Albert Lanier series of stories about growing up in Georgia 2003-09-18, 2003-12-26. Aiko present [38:22] late 40s, moving to SF [40:54] wedding, Ruth at very end [46:28] Side B: Ruth Asawa interviewed by Aiko Cuneo 2003-11-24. "random questions to integrate with other transcripts" re: wedding ring, Buckminster Fuller, intermarriage, how she met Albert, traveling to California, Black Mountain, esp. Fall 1948 as student body president
      Lanier, Albert
    - Addie Lanier interviews Ruth Asawa's longtime friend Mae Lum Lee in prep for de Young Book, 2004-07-19; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Addie Lanier interviews Ruth Asawa's longtime friend Merry Renk in prep for de Young Book, 2004-06-17; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 42, Folder 3)
      Renk, Merry
  - 25.3 slide presentations
    - Alvarado School-Community Arts Program [carousel], 1970s; 1 slide tray(s) (Box 274, Item 1)
    - Oakland Museum [carousel with narrative], 2002-07-14; 1 slide tray(s) (Box 274, Item 2)
  - 25.4 photographs of house, studio, carved doors, garden
    - prints (Box 199, Folder 1)
    - slides (Box 199, Folder 2)
    - snapshots (Box 199, Folders 3-4)
    - oversize (Flat-box 242, Folder 9)
    - City Planning Commission hearing re: Cuneo house expansion [audio], 1991-05-06; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - 25.5 miscellaneous photos and slides
    - Asawa portraits - slides (Box 237, Folder 1)
      Includes youth, Rohwer, Black Mountain, and Imogen Cunningham photos.
    - Rooftop on Ruth. DVD and Photos ["Simple Gifts: Ruth Asawa"], 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 47, Folder 13)
      Titled "Simple Gifts: Ruth Asawa." Still photographs of art workshop with soundtrack. No Ruth, but Hyatt fountain, Oakland Museum sculpture are seen.
    - duplicate slides [four metal cases] (Box 236)
    - art photos, non-Asawa (Box 116, Folders 9-10)
      Snapshots, probably taken by Asawa. Runnymede Sculpture Farm 1990, Djerassi 1991, Vancouver museums 1993, etc.
    - overexposed negatives of Ruth and Albert (Flat-boxes 274, Item 3)
- Series 26. Articles saved by Asawa
  Various articles saved by Ruth, some for portrait ideas, some for reference.
  - Education, 1969-2002 (Box 253, Folders 1-5)
  - Arts Education, 1968-2005 (Box 254, Folder 1)
  - Art, 1965-2006 (Box 254, Folders 2-3)
  - People to Draw (Box 254, Folder 4)
  - People (Box 255, Folders 1-2)
  - Health, Lupus (Box 255, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 255, Folder 4)